<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An invitation of love, to all who hunger and thirst after righteousness, to come and take of the water of life freely without money and without price with a word of advice to such as are asking the way to Sion (and are weeping) with their faces thither-ward : together with a faithful warning to the inhabitants of Babylon, to come out of her, lest (partaking of her sins) ye also come to partake of her plagues / by Isabel Yeamans.</title>
            <author>Yeamans, Isabel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15491</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13031003</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13031003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 403:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An invitation of love, to all who hunger and thirst after righteousness, to come and take of the water of life freely without money and without price with a word of advice to such as are asking the way to Sion (and are weeping) with their faces thither-ward : together with a faithful warning to the inhabitants of Babylon, to come out of her, lest (partaking of her sins) ye also come to partake of her plagues / by Isabel Yeamans.</title>
                  <author>Yeamans, Isabel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96734:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN INVITATION OF LOVE To all who Hunger and Thirſt after Righteouſneſs, to come and take of the Water of Life freely without Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and without Price.</p>
            <p>With a Word of Advice to ſuch as are Asking the WAY to <hi>SION</hi> (and are Weeping) with their Faces thither-ward.</p>
            <p>Together with A faithful Warning to the Inhabitants of BABYLON, to come out of her, leſt (partaking of her Sins) ye alſo come to partake of her Plagues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Iſabel Yeamens.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And I heard a Voice from Heaven, ſaying, Come out of her my People, that ye be not Partakers of her Sins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 18.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:96734:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96734:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen in the weighty and deep Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations of my Heart I beheld the States and Conditions of ſuch as are inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Way to <hi>Sion,</hi> and have ſome tender deſires begotten in them after the Lord, and the Knowledge of his Way; my Life was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly drawn forth in the Love of God, with living breathings unto him (in whom all Fulneſs dwells) that of the Manifeſtation and free Diſpenſations of his Love &amp; Life all ſuch may come to feel and receive, and to take heed of ſleighting the Day of their tender Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilſt the Lord ſecretly calls unto them by his good Spirit in their Boſoms, leſt the Night overtake them, wherein no man can work.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96734:3"/>
            <p> And in the Senſe of the Univerſal Love of God extended unto <hi>All</hi> Mankind, I was conſtrained in my Spirit to commit theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing lines to publick view, as finding my Burden unremoved until I was made willing to communicate the ſame, which I have done with as much brevity as I could with clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, hoping the ponderous Reader, and ſuch whom it chiefly concerns, may not be diſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted at the ſimplicity of the Srile, or my want of Eloquence in expreſſing my ſelf in things of this nature, having herein hinted at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things which I have experienced through the free Love of God to my Soul, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming but little and low things, yet may not miſs of ſome ſervice for the ſtirring up of the ſimple-minded, to make a diligent ſearch how the Caſe ſtands betwixt God and their Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Souls, who thereby coming to ſee their Conditions, and their Neglect and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, in not anſwering the Lord's Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, according to the Manifeſtations and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Diſcoveries of his Light and Grace in their Hearts, may come to redeem their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96734:3"/>Time (which is irrevocable) and take up a Holy Reſolution, by the Aſſiſtance of the Grace of God to redeem their Time to come, by a Godly, Righteous and Sober Converſation, in the Fear of the Lord, and by taking heed to this pure Principle of Light, and Life, may come to be enabled thereby to perform that Duty and acceptable Service which the Lord requires of them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Reward of the Profitable and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Servant, is the Deſire of my Soul.</p>
            <p>And that none may ſleight the Day of ſmall things, but be faithful to what little meaſure the Lord commits to them, and thereby to become worthy of more.</p>
            <p>So not deſirous to be tedious, or to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take great things, I recommend the Reader to the following Lines, whoſe Mind I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be poſſeſſed with ſeriouſneſs, and with the Fear of the Lord, when exerciſed in reading of things relating to Eternity; ſo ſhall ſuch reap Benefit hereby, and anſwer the End of my Labours and Travails, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96734:4"/>is the Well-being of their IMMORTAL SOULS.</p>
            <p>This is chiefly intended for the Northern Parts of this Nation, where many are thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afreſh after the Truth, although igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of it; and that ſuch may be informed of the Way thereto, and reap Everlaſting Life by it, is my Soul's Deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iſabell Yeamans.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96734:4"/>
            <head>An <hi>INVITATION</hi> of <hi>LOVE</hi> to all that Hunger and Thirſt after Righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TO all you who are ignorant of the Way of Life and Salvation, and are ſeeking the Living amongſt the Dead Tombs and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, and are wandring in the Night, in the dead Forms and empty Profeſſions, Will-Worſhips and Traditions of Men, which are ſet up, held and performed in man's Will, and in man's Time, and not in God's Time, nor according to his Mind and Will, and therefore are an abomination unto him.</p>
            <p>Now that all ſuch may be informed aright, my Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony and Exhortation in the Fear of the Lord is, That he is not there, but is ariſen and aſcended far above all Heavens; the Stone is roled from the Door of the Sepulchre, and the Grave-Clothes are left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; the Watch-men of the Night could not hold him, nor the Grave contain him: Oh! look not for him where he is not to be found, as the Angel ſaid to <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> and the other Women, <hi>He is not here, he is riſen,</hi> and they declared his Reſurrection, <hi>John</hi> 10.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.7. Where 'tis manifeſt, that the firſt Witneſſes that were commiſſionated (and that by the Angel of the Lord) to preach the Reſurrection of Chriſt Jeſus, were Women, who (as its written)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96734:5"/>returned with Fear and great Joy, and could not but declare what they had ſeen and heard concerning the Lord Chriſt, though yet it ſeemed to ſome (yea, of the Diſciples themſelves, who were afterwards convinced of the Truth of thoſe Women's Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies) as idle Tales; as it ſeems to many in this Age, becauſe the Reſurrection is held forth and born Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony unto by Women: but bleſſed be the Lord, he hath raiſed up many, both Sons and Daughters, to be living Witneſſes this day of his inward and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Appearance, and Power of his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion. So look not for him in the Shadows and Forms without the Power and Subſtance, nor be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the hearing of him by the hearing of the Ear, or a notional Traditional Knowledge, without the ſaving Knowledge of Power; for until you come to know his Power and Life in your ſelves, to ſave you from Evil, you are not come to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; but are ſtill running from Mountain to Hill, as Sheep having no Shepherd, ſeeking living Bread in deſolate places, and hewing unto your ſelves Ciſterns that will hold no Water (an Evil which the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of among the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) ſaying, <hi>Ye have forſaken me the Fountain of Living Water, and hewn unto your ſelves Ciſterus that can hold no Water.</hi> So come, ye off the Mountains of <hi>Eſau,</hi> into the low Valleys, where the Springs of Life you may feel, and come into the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> where the Lord pleads with all fleſh by Sword &amp; by Fire, that through his deep, Judgment, for Sin and Tranſgreſſion, through true Acknowledgment and Repentane the Valley of <hi>Achor</hi> may be known to be a Door of Hope to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96734:5"/>Tranſgreſſors, and by this Hope through Faith come to receive Chriſt in you the Hope of Glory, who is the Reſurrection of the Juſt unto Life, and of the Unjuſt unto Condemnation; the firſt begotten from the Dead, and the firſt born of every Creature, and now glorified with the Father the Creator of all things; who made the Heavens and the Earth, the Sea, and the Fountains of Water; who formed the Mountains, and created the Winds, and declares un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man what his Thoughts are, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.13. the Lord of Hoſts is his Name: He is making himſelf known in the Hearts of people by his great Power, who will overturn and remove all Mountains and Hills that may be ſhaken or removed, that that alone which cannot be ſhaken may remain; then ſhall the Loftineſs of the Heart of Man be brought down, and the Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs thereof laid low, that all Fleſh may fear and tremble before the Lord, who gives unto all Life, Breath and Being.</p>
            <p>And as Man and Woman comes to believe in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which diſcovers and makes manifeſt unto them the moſt ſecret Thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of their Hearts, that they are continually Evil (in the unregenerate ſtate) for as the Lord ſaid, <hi>Every Imagination of the Heart of Man was only continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> Gen, 6.5. and the Prophet ſaith, <hi>The Heart is Deceitful above all things, and deſperately Wicked; who can know it? I the Lord ſearch the Heart and try the Reins, to give unto every Man according to his Wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Light, I ſay, being believed in, kept to, and obeyed, is able work a Change, and to cleanſe the Heart, that was corrupted by Sin and Tranſgreſſion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96734:6"/>and to beget good Thoughts and good Deſires, and to judge down the contrary, even all the Corrupt Wayes that man in his own Inventions has involved himſelf into, and forſaken his Maker: But this is not of our ſelves, nor by any Acquirement of our own; but is the free Gift of God (the Giver of all good things) which he has given us to believe in; and to him alone (not unto any thing of our ſelves) we aſcribe the Glory and Honour, to whom it is due for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Now, foraſmuch as all men have ſinned, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſhort of the Glory of God, it pleaſed God (out of his infinite Love and Compaſſion towards the Sons and Daughters of Men) to ſend his only begotten Son Chriſt Jeſus a Light into the World, that all through him might be ſaved, and have Everlaſting Life, who gave his Life a Ranſom for all, that he might purchaſe them by his precious Blood; He is the Propitiation for our Sins, and not for our Sins on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo for the Sins of the whole World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. And as man comes to believe in his Name (which is his Power) he comes to know Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through his Death and Blood, and by it Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion up unto God again: And the Everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel (which is the great Power of God unto Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all that believe in it, and obey the ſame) comes here to be witneſſed, which is that Goſpel which Chriſt commanded his Diſciples to preach through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World to every Creature under Heaven, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. And, If any man preach any other Goſpel then that which is already preached and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, let him be accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. But if this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96734:6"/>be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this World hath blinded the minds of them which believe not, leſt the Light of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God ſhould ſhine unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Now this Everlaſting Goſpel is preached again in the ſame Power and Demonſtration of the Spirit, as in times paſt, by virtue whereof Life and Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is again brought to Light; ſo that the Priſoner of Hope comes to receive the acceptable Tidings of Liberty and Freedom out of ſpiritual Bondage and Captivity.</p>
            <p>And the Lord is ariſing and appearing in the Hearts and Conſciences of the Sons and Daughters of men by the bright ſhinings of the Beams of his Glory, to give unto them the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Chriſt Jeſus, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>Now, the Reaſon why people have been erring and wandring every one after their own Wayes, and in the dark Imaginations of their own Hearts is, for want of the Knowledge of the only true God, and Chriſt Jeſus whom he hath ſent (whom to know is Life Eternal) and the Reaſon why People come ſhort of this Knowledge is, becauſe they will not believe in, and yield Obedience unto the Light of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, manifeſted in their Hearts, to give them the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Knowledge of the Lord, and of his Way of Life and Salvation, and to lead them from under Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's power, who hath held people in Ignorance (through Unbelief) and hath kept them under the Region of the Shadow of Death: For Chriſt Jeſus,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96734:7"/>who ſaid, <hi>I am the Light of the World;</hi> alſo ſaid, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye believe that</hi> I AM HE, <hi>ye ſhall dye in your Sins, and whither I go ye cannot come.</hi> So that Unbelief in the Light, was and is the Cauſe why people dye in their Sins, and come ſhort of the Knowledge of God and Jeſus Chriſt, whom to know is Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt Jeſus, who is that Word that was in the Beginning, by which all things were made that were made, in whom was (and is) Life, and the Life was (and is) the Light of Men, <hi>John</hi> 1.4. he is the true Light, that lighteth every man that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the World, by which loſt man comes to ſee his Way to God again out of his miſerable Eſtate and undone Condition, where all Fleſh hath corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its way before the Immortal God; in which way of Corruption (by reaſon of Sin and Tranſgreſſion) there is none that doth good, no not one. And in this fallen Eſtate and deplorable Condition hath the Lord God beheld the Sons and Daughters of fallen <hi>Adam,</hi> and with an Eye of Pity and in the Bowels of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion hath he looked down from the Habitation of his Holineſs, and hath ſent forth the Son of his Love, who (by his Light and Grace) appears in the Hearts of all Mankind; his Light, and his Grace, and good Spirit, is univerſal, and freely extended unto all, that as they mind it, believe in it, and are obediene to it, they come to witneſs Salvation by it, according to the Teſtimony of the holy Apoſtle, <hi>The Grace of God, that bringeth Salvation, hath appeared unto all men, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching us, that denying Ungodlineſs and Worldly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly and godly, &amp;c.</hi> Titus 2.11, 12.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96734:7"/>
            <p> Now there is none excluded from the Appearance of this free Grace of God, nor any to be excuſed who receive it not, and reſit the Teachings of it: But as many as are obedient to the Teachings of it in their own Hearts, they come to witneſs Freedom and Liberty by it, and Power in it to reſiſt the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and many Snares that be in the Ungodly World And thoſe that hate the Reproofs of its Inſtruction (which is the Way of Life) and turn from it into Laſciviouſneſs and Vanity, they will find it to be their Condemnation; and thoſe are they that crucifie unto themſelves afreſh the Lord of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and put him to open ſhame, and trample the Blood of the Covenant under foot, as a thing of no value: And here the Lamb lies ſlain in the Streets of the Ungodly World (ſpiritually called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt</hi>) that his got a place in man's Heart ſince the Fall. The Foundation of this wicked World, that is in Sin &amp; Polution, that has ſo corrupted the Earth, and filled it with Violence, was laid by Tranſgreſſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Death came over all men. But as by the Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of one Man, All have ſinned, and fallen ſhort of the Glory of God; ſo by the Obedience of one Man (the Man Chriſt Jeſus) we come to be made alive again: And as the Creature comes to joyn with the Manifeſtation of the Light of Chriſt Jeſus (the free Gift of the Father's Love, who is full of Grace and Truth) they come to know and feel his quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, which ſets free from the Law of Sin and Death: And keeping to the Light, which diſcovers all the Deeds of Darkneſs, they come to ſee their Way out of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> to Chriſt the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96734:8"/>and how to refuſe the Evil, and chuſe the Good, according as in the Light it is made manifeſt; for, as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>All things that are reproved are made manifeſt by the Light; for whatſoever doth make manifeſt, is Light,</hi> Epheſ. 5.13.</p>
            <p>Now mind that in your own Hearts which repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in ſecret, when no mortal Eye ſees, nor Ear hears the ſmall ſtill Voice, which calls unto you when you are running to do Evil, which grieves the Spirit of the Lord in you: Return, return, hearken unto the Voice of Wiſdom; for ſhe uttereth her Voice in the Streets of the World, and in the midſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the People, <hi>How long ye ſimple ones will ye love Simplicity, and Scorners delight in their Scorning, and Fools hate Knowledge? Turn ye at my Reproofs, &amp;c. Becauſe I have called, and ye have refuſed; I have ſtretched forth my Hand, and none regarded; but ye have deſpiſed all my Counſel, and would none of my Reproof; I will alſo laugh at your Calamity, when your Fear cometh like a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and when Affliction and Anguiſh ſhall come upon you. Then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not anſwer; they ſhall ſeek me early, but ſhall not find me; becauſe they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Knowledge, and did not chuſe the Fear of the Lord: But whoſo hearkeneth unto me, ſhall dwell ſafely,</hi> Prov. 1.22, 23, 24.</p>
            <p>Here the Wiſe Man in the Wiſdom of God ſhews what is to be turned from, and the Safety, Peace and Conſolation of thoſe that turn at the Reproofs, and hearken to the Voice of this pure Wiſdom; as alſo, the Calamity and Diſtreſs of ſuch as will not give ear to the Reproofs of Inſtruction (which, as one ſaid, is the Way to Life) nor be obedient to the Meaſure
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96734:8"/>of Light and Life in their Hearts, ſuch muſt reap the Fruit of their own Devices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaking excellently and experimentally of this Wiſdom, ſaith on this wiſe; <hi>Where is Wiſdom to be found? and where is the place of Underſtanding? Man knoweth not the Price thereof. The Depth ſaith, It is not in me; and the Sea ſaith, It is not in me: It cannot be gotten for Gold, neither ſhall Silver be weighed for the Price thereof. But</hi> THE FEAR OF THE LORD <hi>that is Wiſdom; and</hi> TO DEPART FROM INI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUITY, <hi>that is a good Underſtanding. Death and Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction have heard of the Fame of Wiſdom;</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny can talk of it; but they are Aliens to it, and their Hearts remote from it. Oh! the pure holy Fear of the Lord God, it keeps the Heart clean, it preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth out of all Evil, and delivers from the Snares of Death; it is a precious Pearl indeed, a matchleſs Jewel: Where is the Man that is furniſhed with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, to unfold the Excellency of this Wiſdom? or who knows the Worth of it? but thoſe who have digged and ſearched the Deep for it, and when they have found it, ſold all their Treaſure, that they have been heaping up in their Notional and Artificial Wiſdom, which is from below, and made a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of this precious Treaſure and Riches, which endures forever; ſuch have made a bleſſed exchange, never to be repented of; the Thief cannot break through and ſteal, nor Moth corrupt, neither can Canker ruſt or eat this Treaſure. But this is not to be found or attained unto in the Path where the Lyons Whelp hath trodden (the fierce angry Nature) or the fierce Lyon has paſſed by; no Vultures Eye nor
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96734:9"/>Beaſt of Prey can walk therein. <hi>And though the Lyons may ſuffer Hunger, yet thoſe that fearthe Lord ſhall want no good thing</hi> (a bleſſed Priviledge indeed.) It was the Fear of the Lord that preſerved <hi>Joſeph</hi> in his tender Years, when he was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and when the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Woman (his Miſtreſs) tempted him: <hi>How can I</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>do this great Wickedneſs, and ſin againſt God?</hi> Gen. 39.9. The Dread and Fear of offending the Lord was before his Eyes, whereby he was preſerved out of that Snare. Oh that people would lay theſe things to heart! and conſider what they are a doing, and ſearch their Hearts in the Light and Fear of the Lord, and humble themſelves before him (to whom they muſt give a juſt and final Account of the Deeds done in the Body) that they may receive Mercy at his Hand, before the Door be ſhut, and there be none to open.</p>
            <p>For ſaith the Lord by the Mouth of his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>I ſaith, waſh you, make you clean, put away the Evil of your Doings from before mine Eyes, ceaſe to do Evil, learn to do well, then come and let us reaſon together; though your Sins were as Crimſon, they ſhall be made white as Snow; though they were red as Scarlet, they ſhall be as Wool: If ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of the Land; but if ye refuſe and be rebellious, ye ſhall be devoured with the Sword, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Son of God ſaith, <hi>Come unto me all you that are weary and heavy laden</hi> (with your Sins and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities (and know not whither to go) <hi>and I will give you Reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is Glad Tidings of an Acceptable Reſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, unto all who are weary with travelling in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96734:9"/>By Wayes and Crooked Pathes, which lead to the Chambers of Death. And this Reſt remains for all the People of God, who have been willing to come unto Chriſt (by his Light in their own Hearts) and to bow to his Appearance.</p>
            <p>And all you who are in want of this Reſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the attainment of it, but are ignorant of the Way that leads to it, my Exhortation and Advice unto you is, to come unto him who ſaid, <hi>Come unto me all you that are weary &amp;c.</hi> of whom it was teſtified, <hi>That when he ſhould come, he ſhould reprove the world of Sin, of Righteouſneſs and of Judgment;</hi> and ceaſe from ſeeking and ſtriving in your own Wills (which is not according to the Will of God) and reſt from your own Labours (as God did from his) &amp; mind that which diſcovers Sin, and reproves in ſecret for it, and turn at the Reproofs of it (which is the Way of Life) as one well experienced, and teſtified in his day; <hi>The Commandment is a LAMP, and the Law is LIGHT, and the Reproofs of Inſtruction THE WAY OF LIFE,</hi> Prov. 6.23. This is that Lamp and that Light of which <hi>David</hi> teſtified, ſaying, <hi>Thy Word is a Lamp unto my Feet, and a Light unto my Paths,</hi> Pſalm 119.105. He alſo ſaid, <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect, converting the Soul;</hi> and is that Word of which he ſaid, <hi>Wherewithal ſhall a Young Man cleanſe his Wayes? by taking heed thereto, according to thy Word:</hi> Which Word, Light, Law, Lamp, Grace, Spirit, &amp;c. with many other Names and Denominations, are one and the ſame in nature and quality, though proceeding from the holy Spirit and Power in the holy Men of God under ſeveral Names and Appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96734:10"/>according to the various Effects, Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Manifeſtations and Operations of it in their Hearts; as when it manifeſteth unto man the Evil of his Wayes, it is properly called <hi>Light;</hi> and as it judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and condemneth for Sin and Evil, it may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Law-giver</hi> and a <hi>Judge,</hi> &amp;c. this is able to deliver and ſet free from the Power of Sin and Death, and to bring loſt man to God again: It was ſufficient under every Diſpenſation for the Recovery and Salvation of Mankind, as it was obeyed and believed in, by which the Righteous Seed and Holy Men of God found Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with the Lord, and knew <hi>that they pleaſed him, and walked with him,</hi> as <hi>Enoch</hi> did, and were made <hi>perfect,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, to whom the Lord ſaid <hi>Walk thou before me, and be thou perfect,</hi> Gen. 17.1.</p>
            <p>But is now manifeſted in theſe latter days in a more Glorious and Evangelical Appearance, wherein the Lord has fulfilled his Promiſe of old, and is pouring forth of his Spirit upon all Fleſh, and is cauſing his Sons and his Daughters to propheſie, and to declare of his wondrous Works: and now Chriſt Jeſus is manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting himſelf in his inward and ſpiritual Appearance of Light in the Hearts and Conſciences of all men, who <hi>is come a Light into the World, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves on him might not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life;</hi> and in this Manifeſtation of his Spirit he is calling and inviting the Sons and Daughters of men, <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I ſtand at the Door and knock; if any man hear any Voice, and open unto me, I will come in and ſup with him, and he with me,</hi> Rev. 3.20. <hi>It is the Voice of my Beloved that knocks, ſaying, Open unto me; for my Head is filled with Dew; and my Locks with the Drops of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96734:10"/>Night,</hi> Song of Sol. 5.2. The Diſobedient and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious will not entertain him in their Hearts; but he is pierced by their Iniquities, and as a Lamb ſlain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Door, and as killed all the day long as to them (though in himſelf he lives to judge them) <hi>He made his Grave with the Wicked, and with the Rich in his Death,</hi> Iſa. 53.9. But the Lord beholds the Proud afar off, who think they know enough, and are fat and full, and want nothing, when they are miſerable, and naked, and bare, and want all things; but the Humble he teacheth, and dwells with the Contrite in Heart; for it is in the Heart and Conſciences of Men and Women where he ought to dwell, and it is his Prerogative to ſway the Scepter there; although the old Uſurper of Authority (called the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi>) by his Stratagems and Inſinuations, has gotten a large Room and open Entertainment in the Hearts of the Children of Diſobedience, ſo that the Inn is taken up with other Gueſts (the vain Delights and Pleaſures of the World) and no room is left to entertain the Lord of Glory, but he is as laid in the Manger, and turned out of Doors, and his ſmall Appearance ſleighted and rejected by the Ungodly: But now is the Prince of Peace come, and is ariſing in his glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Power, to diſ-throne the grand Enemy of man's Happineſs, and to diſcover his many Snares, Baits and Temptations, which he has laid ſuitable to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity and Inclination of the Creature, to betray the Simple-minded, and to draw forth the Heart and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections after his Inventions, thereby to enſlave and imbondage the Creature in Sin and Iniquity, and to plunge it therein, until the Cuſtom of it comes to take
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96734:11"/>away the ſenſe of the Evil of it, and then perſwades the poor Captive, <hi>There is no Freedom from it, nor no Perfection to be attained on this ſide the Grave;</hi> and here he labours to keep them under his Power whilſt in this Life, knowing that <hi>after Death, Judgment comes;</hi> and <hi>as the Tree falls, ſo it lies;</hi> and <hi>that there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in the Grave;</hi> and here he obtains his End, which is the <hi>Eternal</hi> Deſtruction of Men and Womens Souls; for he laid the Foundation of his Kingdom in the Heart of Man and Woman by a Lye, through which Sin entred, and by which he upholds his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to this day in all the Diſobedient and Rebellious. But in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus (which diſcovers all the Deeds of Darkneſs) is he clearly ſeen, and his rotten Foundation, which was grounded upon a Lye, begins now to ſhake and reel, and the Down-fall of his Kingdom is now ſeen to approach by them whoſe Eyes the Lord has opened. But as for thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe this Inward and Evangelical Appearance of Light and Grace, and call it <hi>Natural.</hi> or <hi>the Check of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Conſcience, and a thing Inſufficient (though obeyed) to Salvation;</hi> nay, many will not ſtick to call it <hi>Dia bolical:</hi> whoever they be that are in this ſtate, I am bold to affirm and teſtifie, <hi>That the ſame Power (call it what they will) that ſecretly checks and reproves for Sin and Evil in the Canſciences of Men and Women the ſame (in the Day of Account) ſhall ſet the Sins of the Wicked and Diſobedient in order before their Eyes, and ſhall be their Judge in that Day, and as a Stone that ſhall grind them to Powder; and on the contrary, to thoſe that love it and obey it, will be the Joy, Comfort and Everlaſting Salvation of their Immortal Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96734:11"/>
            <p> Now the Reaſon why people hate the Light, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evident from Chriſt's own words, who ſaith, <hi>This is the Condemnation, that Light is come into the World, and men love Darkneſs rather than Light,</hi> becauſe their Deeds are Evil, <hi>for every one that doth Evil, hateth the Light, neither cometh to the Light, leſt his Deeds ſhould be repreved,</hi> John 3.19, 20. <hi>But he that doth Truth, loves the Light, and brings his Deeds to it, that they may be proved and tryed that they are wrought in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Serpent in his Subtilty is the ſame at this day that he was in the Beginning, who in direct Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Command of God told <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve That in the day they did eat of the Forbidden Fruit they ſhould</hi> Not <hi>ſurely dye, but ſhould be as Gods knowing Good and Evil:</hi> and here was the Temptation laid under the preſentation of an Higher Attainment, or that it was higher or of further Latitude, which certainly was more pernicious and Deſtructive; for, until the Temptation was entred into, they had not the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Evil by participation, but were clothed with the Sweet Innocent Life of God, which he breathed into them, and dwelt in Covenant with their Maker. But after the Enemy had prevailed, and had ſubjected the Creature unto Vanity (as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> 8. verſ. 20.) not willingly, but in Hope of an Higher Attainment, or Better State than that wherein the Lord had placed them, they were betrayed, and loſt their Habitation by breaking the Command of God, and loſt the Heavenly Dignity and Excellency of the firſt Creation, and became dead as to that ſweet Unity, Fellowſhip and Acceſs they had unto God: and here the Serpent was found a Lyar, who told them,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96734:12"/>
               <hi>They ſhould not ſurely dye, &amp;c.</hi> So here Man and Woman were drove out of the Paradiſe of God, and became degenerate Plants of a ſtrange Vine, branching forth it ſelf into many Corrupt Trees, whoſe Fruit have been <hi>Envy, Wrath, Murder</hi> and <hi>Perſecution about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Sacrifice and Worſhip, Pride, Emulation, Deceit</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſie;</hi> and in theſe evil Branches have the unclean Birds and the Fowls of the Air lodged, and the Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice, that comes out of the Serpent's Root, whoſe Fruit (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>ſhall be a Fiery Flying Serpent,</hi> Iſa. 14.29.</p>
            <p>Now the Cockatrice hath been hatching and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth her Cage of unclean Birds by the power of the Serpent, whereby they are become Birds of Prey, to the perſecuting of the Innocent Birth or good Seed of the Kingdom, and quenching the good Deſires which are in the Hearts of People. But as the firſt Appearance or Motion to Evil is reſiſted and turned from, the Conception thereof is prevented in the Heart (for 'tis there that Sin is conceived, before 'tis brought forth into action) and the Cockatrice comes to be cruſhed in the Egg, before it is brought forth to be a Bird of Prey, and the Creature preſerved out of the Snare, And ſo it may be ſeen, that this Crooked Serpent has been the ground Cauſe of all the Wo and Miſery that is come upon Mankind, who ſeeks to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray and deceive the Innocent, as he did <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> who actually knew no Evil, until under a fair Pretence he preſented the forbidden fruit unto <hi>Eve</hi> (the weaker Veſſel) who by hearkening unto him did eat, and gave alſo to her Husband, and ſo brought Death over themſelves, according as the Lord God had ſaid,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96734:12"/>
               <hi>In the day that ye eat thereof, ye ſhall dye.</hi> Thus by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the Righteous Law of God, in eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit, Sin entred, and Death by Sin, which is come upon all, and all have fallen ſhort of the Glory of God. And they that are feeding of the Tree of Knowledge without Life, are under the ſame Sentence of Death, which was paſſed over <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> through their Diſobedience. So Death reigned from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes, even over them who had not ſinned after the ſimilitude of</hi> Adam<hi>'s Tranſgreſſion,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>For as by the Offence of one, Judgment came upon all men to Condemnation; even ſo by the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of one, the free Gift came upon all unto Juſtification of Life,</hi> Rom. 5.18. And as many as receive the free Gift of Grace and Righteouſneſs, ſhall reign in Life by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And in this free Gift of God (in which is Life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) comes Man and Woman to inherit their former Priviledge and Right to the Tree of Life again: for the univerſal Loving-kindneſs of the Lord God was ſuch towards the Noble Workmanſhip of his Hands, that notwithſtanding Man and Woman had tranſgreſſed the holy righteous Law of the Lord, and being firſt violated by the Woman, yet he promiſed, <hi>That the Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpent's Head;</hi> and to the Serpent he ſaid, <hi>I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman, and between thy Seed and her Seed; it ſhall bruiſe thy Head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his Heel,</hi> Gen. 3.15.</p>
            <p>This faithful Promiſe, in which the Patriarchs of old, with the Prophets and Holy Men of God belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, in the Fulneſs of time came to be fulfilled, and the Virgin conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96734:13"/>Overſhadowing of the Power of the Moſt High, and brought forth that Holy Thing whoſe Name was called <hi>Jeſus,</hi> according as the Angel of the Lord had fore-told unto <hi>Mary,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed art thou among Women, thou haſt found Favour with God; for lo, thou ſhalt conceive in thy womb, and bear a Son, and ſhalt call his Name</hi> Jeſus. Now <hi>Mary</hi> reaſoned a little, ſaying, <hi>How can this be, ſeeing I know not Man?</hi> To whom the Angels Anſwer was, <hi>The Holy Choſt ſhall come upon thee, and the Power of the Moſt High ſhall everſhadow thee; therefore that Holy Thing that ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God.</hi> So <hi>Mary</hi> conſulted no more, but believing the Angel, ſaid, <hi>Be it unto me according to thy word,</hi> Luke 1.35. And in the overcoming Senſe of the Joy which through Faith ſhe had received, ſaid on this wiſe, <hi>My Soul doth magnifie the Lord, and my Spirit rejoyceth in God my Saviour; from henceforth all Generations ſhall call me bleſſed, becauſe be that is mighty has done great things for me, and Holy is his Name.</hi> So in the Seed Chriſt Jeſus, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that never fell, who is made a quickening Spirit, comes the Bleſſing again to be obtained, and all thoſe that believe in him come to be redeemed from under the Curſe, and to know his Spirit as a Standard lifted up in them, to the cruſhing and breaking down the Head of the Serpent (which is his Power) ſo that the Enmity that is put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Seeds ſhall never be reconciled; and as this Seed of Life, which the good Seedſman has ſown in every Heart, comes to take root and grow, it will ſuppreſs and keep under the Evil Seed of the Serpent, which brings forth Bryars and Thorns, to entangle the Soul as in a Net, whoſe End is to be burnt up and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96734:13"/>conſumed by the Breath of the Lord. And although the Enemy has come in the Night, and hath ſown Tares and Brambles in the Field (which is the World) where the good Seed was ſown, yet mark, <hi>their End is to be cut down at the time of Harveſt (which is the end of the World) and to be bundled up, and caſt into the Fire unquenchable.</hi> Oh! what will become of all thoſe in that day, who have ſuffered the Tares and Brambles to grow, &amp; have not believed nor put Confidence in, but obſtinately reſiſted the <hi>appearance</hi> of Chriſt, the benefit of whoſe Sufferings, Death, Reſurrection and Aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuch might have received, and have been cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all their evil Wayes and corrupt Devices by Chriſt Jeſus, who <hi>is come a Light into the World, that whoſoever believes in him, ſhould not abide in Darkneſs, but have the Light of Life,</hi> John 8.12. he teſtified of himſelf, ſaying, <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the Life; he that believes in me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live:</hi> this is he to whom all the ends of the Earth are to look for Salvation; he is the <hi>Shiloh,</hi> the <hi>peaceable Saviour,</hi> who is now come according to <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Prophecy upon his dying Bed, ſaying, <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from Judah, <hi>nor a Law-giver from between his Feet, until</hi> Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh <hi>come, and unto him ſhall the gathering of the People be,</hi> Gen 49.10. (which Scepter of Government is long ſince departed from <hi>Judah,</hi> therefore <hi>Shiloh</hi> is come) Now the ſpiritual Scepter is deliver'd unto him, who, without Reſpect of Perſons, is holding it forth unto all Nations, Kindreds, Tongues and People, that his Government may be ſet up, and his Scepter ſway in their Hearts, <hi>whoſe Kingdom is an Everlaſting Kingdom, and of his Dominion there ſhall be no End;</hi> upon whoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96734:14"/>Shoulders the Government is ſet, and the Nations of them that are ſaved muſt walk in the Light of the Lamb, who is come to take away the ſins of the world, &amp; has brought a Remnant (through their Belief in and Obedience unto the Light of Chriſt) to the knowledge of his ſaving Power, which brings out of the dead Forms to the living Subſtance, which gives true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the Soul: And ſuch cannot but ſay unto and invite all, who hunger and thirſt after Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>To come and taſte with us, and ſee how good the Lord is; for it is that which was from the Beginning, which we have ſeen with our Eyes, which we have looked upon, and our Hands have handled of the Word of Life, that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you, that you alſo might have fellowſhip with us, and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> John 1.3. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride ſaith Come, and let him that heareth ſay Come, and he that is athirſt let him come, and take of the Waters of Life freely,</hi> Rev. 22.17. Oh! why will you ſpend your Money for that which is not Bread, and your Labour for that which doth not ſatisfie your Souls, who with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal have ſpent your Portion, and are feeding upon the Husks in your Notional Self Performances, and Imitations of true Religion, Sacrifice and Worſhip? But alas! it is not the Profeſſion, Shew or Likeneſs of theſe things (without the Poſſeſſion of that Life and Power in which they are accepted of the Lord) that will ſtand in ſtead in the needful time; for 'tis not a ſight or ſhew of Food that will ſatisfie an hungry or travelling Man; but <hi>Give me Bread</hi> (ſayes the hungry Soul) <hi>or elſe I dye</hi>—Oh! how doth my Spirit mourn for thoſe who are ſeeking living Bread among the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96734:14"/>Husks, where its not to be found, and are inquiring after their Souls Beloved, and are running from one Watchman to another, ſeeking the Footſteps of the Flock of his Companions, and where he feeds them, and cauſes them to lie down at noon day. Come you that have been enquiring of the blind Watchmen of the Night, I will tell you where we have found the Beloved of our Souls (where you alſo muſt find him) The Spouſe of old ſought him amongſt the Watchmen, yet found him not; <hi>But,</hi> ſayes ſhe, <hi>when I had paſt a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle from them, then I found him whom my Soul loved:</hi> Such was our inquiring Condition amongſt the blind <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Night,</hi> who cryed, <hi>Lo here</hi> and <hi>Lo there,</hi> whoſe Trumpet gave an uncertain ſound unto us, and inſtead of Relief cauſed our Wounds to bleed afreſh, telling us, <hi>Revelation was ceaſed and we muſt not expect God &amp; Chriſt in that inward and ſpiritual Appearance wherein he made known himſelf to his People in dayes paſt; but we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to this outward Ceremony, and the other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, &amp;c.</hi> and thus they ſmote us and wounded us: But bleſſed be our God forever, who turned us from them, to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which gave us the knowledge of our Beloved, and directed our Feet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right Way, even the Juſt Man's Path, which is a ſhining Light, and ſhines more and more unto the perfect day, &amp; the Wayfaring Man (though a Fool) ſhall not err therein. So it was by the inſhinings of his Light &amp; Grace in our Hearts, that we received the Diſcovery and Knowledge of our Beloved, who is become the chiefeſt of ten thouſand unto a Remnant, as he was to the Spouſe of old: He is the Door into the Sheepfold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the true Shepherd, who laid down his Life for his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96734:15"/>Sheep; and whoever enters into this heavenly Fold of Reſt and Peace, muſt enter in by his Light, who is the Door; for <hi>whoever climb up any other way, are Thieves and Robbers;</hi> and his Sheep hear his Voice, and the Voice of a Stranger they will not follow, becauſe they can clearly diſtinguiſh between the true Shepherd and the falſe Shepherds (who whilſt people put into their Mouthes cry <hi>Peace, Peace;</hi> and when not fed, prepare War againſt them) witneſs the many grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sufferings of Innocent People in Body &amp; Eſtate; how many naſty Goals have been crouded full by their Cruelty? how many Wives have been made Widows and Children Fatherleſs (whoſe Cryes have pierced the Heavens, and whoſe Complaint has entred the Ears of the Lord) by their <hi>unrighteouſneſs</hi> &amp; <hi>inhuman dealings with God's people:</hi> And how have theſe Idol Shepherds, who have ſought the Fleece, and not regarded the Sheep, like Wolves and Bears, rended the Goods of ſuch as could not put into their Mouthes, the impartial Reader and every unbyaſs'd Mind can well inform. But the great and powerful Shepherd, the mighty God, hath taken Cognizance of theſe things, and will ſurely call them to account, and reckon with them in a Day that is come &amp; coming upon them, wherein they ſhall be more and more made manifeſt, that they are not ſent of God, nor true Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe they abide not in his Doctrine, who ſaid, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give:</hi> and if any ſhall ask, <hi>How we know them?</hi> we need go no further then the words of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>By their Fruits ye ſhall know them;</hi> for they are ſuch who <hi>ſeek their Gain from their Quarter, who feed with the fat and clothe with the Wool, and love the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96734:15"/>Rooms at Feaſts, and Greetings in the Market-place,</hi> with divers other Marks, whereby we know them to be ſuch as ran and God never ſent them, and their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to be erroneous and unprofitable. But the Sheep of Chriſt's Paſture are clothed with the Lamb-like, Meek, Quiet and Suffering Spirit of Jeſus, who makes his Followers conformable unto himſelf, that in all things we may be found followers of him in his Light and Grace, who hath other Sheep which are not of this Fold, whom alſo he ſaid ſhould be brought in, that they may hear his Voice; <hi>and there ſhall be one Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and one Shepherd,</hi> John 10.16. And for thoſe Sheep who are not yet gathered into this Fold, doth my Soul travail, that they with us might partake of the living Bread, which comes down from Heaven. <hi>I am that living Bread</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that came down from Heaven. My Fleſh is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink indeed; whoever eats of the Bread and drinks of the Water that I give, ſhall never hunger nor thirſt any more: Except ye eat my Fleſh and drink my Blood, ye have no Life in you.</hi> This was an hard Saying to the profeſſing <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe Eye was outward and carnal; as it is with many this day, who make a great talk of his Fleſh and Blood: But except you have Faith in his Name, and by virtue of that Faith come to eat his Fleſh and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you; for, ſayes he, (who ſais, <hi>I am the Light) Except ye believe that I am he, ye ſhall dye in your Sins, and whither I go ye cannot come.</hi> so that it is Unbelief in his Light or Grace in people which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoints them of the benefit of his Blood, which clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, waſhes and ſanctifies all thoſe that believe in his Name and Power, by which, as they keep unto and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in it, they come to witneſs their Redeemer to live,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96734:16"/>even Chriſt, the Anointed of God, the Everlaſting Miniſter of the Sanctuary, and of the true Tabernacle, which God hath pitched, and not Man; he is become our High Prieſt, and the Biſhop of our Souls; he is teaching his People himſelf; and our Invitation unto all is, that they may come and ſit down under the Teachings of his Spirit and Grace in themſelves; <hi>For, whatſoever may be known of God is manifeſt within;</hi> and he hath ſhewn unto Man what is good, that he ſhould obey it and do it; and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Examine your ſelves, prove your ſelves; know ye not your own ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except ye be Reprobates.</hi> Now thou who haſt had thine Eye outward, &amp; haſt bin run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning abroad, and ſpent thy Portion with the Prodigal, and haſt not obtained an Eſtabliſhment in that which is durable and ſatisfying the Soul; Return, return to thy Father's Houſe, and turn thy Mind inward to that which thou haſt run from, and haſt been ſeeking with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, and thou wilt find virtue in it, and the Efficacy of it to ſatisfie thy breathing Soul: for, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Parable of the Woman, who ſought her piece of Silver without her Houſe, but turning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, lighting a Candle, and ſweeping her Houſe, ſhe found it, and for the Joy that ſhe had found this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, invited her Neighbours to come and rejoyce with her. Now the Candle of the Lord (which is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a Man) is lighted, and the Houſes of many are ſwept, and that which they have been ſeeking without they have found within them, to the exceeding great Joy &amp; Gladneſs of their Hearts, ſo that they could not but invite and perſwade others (through the conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Virtue and Soul-ſatisfaction they had receiv'd from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96734:16"/>it) to turn in to that inward Word of Power which is nigh, in the Heart, and is a ſure Word of Prophecy, <hi>unto which</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi>) ye do well to take heed, as unto a Light ſhining in a dark place, until the Day dawn, and the Day Star ariſe in your Hearts,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19.</p>
            <p>Now we having taken heed unto this divine and heavenly Word in our Hearts, we are come to ſee the ariſing of the Star of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to the bright and morning Star, by which the bleſſed Day of God's great Salvation is known and experimentally witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a Remnant. Oh! how glorious is the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance &amp; breaking forth of this heavenly Day, in which the riſing of the Son of Righteouſneſs (who is riſen with Healing under his Wings) many are come to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; how excellent is the Power, Wiſdom and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of him who is greater than <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Order, Magnificency and Splendor the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> from the uttermoſt parts of the Earth, came to ſee, who when ſhe had heard and ſeen all that ſhe deſired (yea to her Aſtoniſhment) made this acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, <hi>I believed not this Report, until I had ſeen it with mine Eyes; but lo, the one half was not told me; for thou haſt more Wiſdom and Proſperity than I have heard by Report,</hi> 1 Kings 10.7. And many can now ſay, that a <hi>Greater</hi> than <hi>Solomon</hi> is now come, whoſe infinite Wiſdom and Power, whoſe excellent Glory and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty the Tongues of Men and Angels are incapable and inſufficient to ſet forth, who is filling his latter Houſe with the Splendor of his own Glory, for tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending and ſurpaſſing the Glory of the Outward Temple, which was typical &amp; figurative of that which is not built with Hands; and many Sons are coming
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96734:17"/>from far, and Daughters from the ends of the Earth, to behold the Beauty and Comlineſs and Holy Order of the Houſe of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which he is eſtabliſhing atop of all the exalted Mountains and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions without Poſſeſſion, and above all ſwelling Notions and Hills, and Nations are flowing unto it, according as the Lord ſpake by the Mouth of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Beautiful fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tuation is Mount</hi> Sion (the Hill of God) and it is now fulfilled in theſe latter days, that many are come to ſay, <hi>Let us go up to the Mountain of the Lord, and to the Houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he will teach us of his Wayes, and we will walk in his Pathes.</hi> Theſe are the true <hi>Jews</hi> in Spirit, the Circumciſed in Heart &amp; Ear, whoſe Praiſe is of God, and not of men: ſuch are the true Worſhippers, who worſhip the Father in the Spirit and in the Truth, which is that living, true and ſtanding Worſhip) ſet up and eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſixteen hundred years ago, by our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, in that bleſſed Conference held with the <hi>woman</hi> of <hi>Samaria</hi> at <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well, who hearing of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes &amp; various Opinions about the Place where men ought to worſhip, ſaid, <hi>Woman, believe me, The Hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain nor at</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>worſhip the Father; for the Hour cometh and now is, that the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and Truth; and ſuch is the Father ſeeking to worſhip him, John</hi> 4.21, 23. This Woman, by this Converſe with Chriſt, being converted to the Faith in him, went her way into the City, and gave this Teſtimony of him, <hi>Come ſee a Man</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>that has told me all that ever I have done; is not this the Chriſt?</hi> And many of the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> believ'd on him, not only becauſe of the ſaying of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96734:17"/>the Woman, who told them, <hi>That he had told her all that ever ſhe had done,</hi> but becauſe of his own Word: <hi>And we know</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that this is indeed the Chriſt.</hi> Now theſe men were directed unto Chriſt by the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Preaching of a Woman, who was not deſpiſed by them becauſe of her Sex, but they received her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, &amp; came to be made Believers in him, who had told the Woman all that ſhe had done; and well were it for the People of this Nation if they would be of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> Mind, and believe in that inward Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Power, which lets them ſee and tells them all that they do and reproves them for Sin and Evil. Now, God is a Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they that worſhip him aright<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt worſhip him in &amp; by the divine Aſſiſtance of his Spirit; but thoſe who deride and make a Mock at the Spirit, and the Guidings and Leadings of it, are known to be out of the Spirit, neither know the Truth, bat are Enemies to it; and all their Worſhips, Duties, Self-Performances, Offerings &amp; Sacrifices out of the Truth, are an Abomination unto the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let their Pretence be never ſo ſpecious: Now <hi>God in his Love hath given a Meaſure of his Spirit unto</hi> All <hi>people, whereby (through Obedience thereto) they may be enabled to perform that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Service he requires of them:</hi> and they that come to feel ſuch a good Deſire and holy Thirſt begotten in them (as did the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi>) after the Water of Life, ſuch by purſuance after the ſame in the Faith, come to receive Satiſfaction and Refreſhment from the Fountain Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaid unto the Woman, <hi>If thou knew'ſt the Gift of God, and who it is that ſaith unto thee [Give we to drink] thou wouldſt have ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him, who would have given thee living Water: thoſe</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96734:18"/>(ſaid he) <hi>that drink of this Water</hi> (ſpeaking of the Water in <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well) <hi>ſhall thirſt again; but whoſoever ſhall drink of the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt; but the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a Well of Water ſpringing up unto Everlaſting Life.</hi> The Woman ſaid unto him, <hi>Sir, give me of this Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that I thirſt not again, &amp;c.</hi> So it appears this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was ignorant of the Gift of God, though it was in her; yet by believing in and receiving his gracious Words, ſhe became acquainted with the true Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Gift of God in her ſelf (as are all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and ſpiritual Worſhippers at this day) and thereby to receive the ingrafted Word with Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is able to ſave the Soul, in and through which the true Worſhippers offer up an acceptable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice within the Gates of the New and Heavenly <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> which <hi>John</hi> ſaw <hi>coming down from God out of Heaven, as a Bride adorned for her Husband, Salvation is the Walls of this holy City, and her Gates Praiſes; neither in her is there need of the Light of the Sun, or of the Moon or Stars, but the Lord God and the Lamb is the Light thereof; and the Nations of them that are ſaved muſt walk in the Light of it,</hi> rev. 21.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Now we, who are come to witneſs this defirable and glorious Habitation of Reft and Peace (which through many deep Sufferings, Cryes and Travails of our anxious Spirits we have mourned for, ſought after and obtained) we cannot but declare unto others in the Love of God, with tender Pity and Compaſſion unto their Souls, who are toſſed about with every Wind of Dectrine (as a Ship in a ſtorm) and even labour to perſwade ſuch, who are thus diſtreſſed, to lay hold
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96734:18"/>on the great Salvation of God, which he in and by his Son Chriſt Jeſus, has freely tendred unto all People, to be his Salvation to the Ends of the Earth, <hi>a Light to lighten the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and to be the Glory of his People</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; this is he whom good old <hi>Simeon</hi> ſaw in his day, when he was waiting for the Conſolation of <hi>Iſrael, Luke</hi> 2.25.</p>
            <p>And you who are looking for Chriſt without you, in the outward Forms and Traditions, my Advice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you is, To turn to that Principle in your own hearts that is meek and lowly; for ſayes Chriſt, <hi>Learn of me, I am meek and low in heart, and ye ſhall find Reſt unto your Souls,</hi> Mat. 11.29. <hi>The Humble he teacheth his Way, and the Meek will he guide in Judgment:</hi> This is the good Phyſician of Value, who hath brought Balm from <hi>Gilead,</hi> and gives Health to the wounded Soul; he waſhes and thoroughly cleanſes the Wound; &amp; when all that has poluted and defiled the Heart and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is purged and done away, then he pours in of his precious Oyntment, which gives a fragrant ſmell to thoſe who have been poluted and defiled by reaſon of Sin, of which the Oyntment was a Figure, that was poured upon <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Head, and run down to the Skirts of his Garment, and was precious; and if that was precious which was outward and typical, how much more is this which is an inward and ſpiritual Unction (which only can reach the Soul, as that did the Body) and which comes from Chriſt, who is anointed with the heavenly Oyl above his Fellows, by vertue of which inward Anointing Health &amp; Soundneſs of heart and mind comes to be known again by thoſe who through this Univerſal Grace receive it; a meaſure of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96734:19"/>which Grace is committed to every one to profit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, if they would prove it and try it, it is one and the ſame in Nature and Quality, though not in Quantity; <hi>For unto one he gave five Talents, to another two, and to another one, and to every man according to their ſeveral Abilities,</hi> in the leaſt of which is ſufficientcy (if obey'd and improv'd) <hi>and where much is given, much is required:</hi> But the wicked and ſloathful Servant, who had but one Talent, counted the Lord an <hi>hard Maſter,</hi> becauſe he was negligent and careleſs to improve it, and hid his Talent in the Earth; but read his Portion; was he not <hi>caſt into utter Darkneſs, where is weeping and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Teeth?</hi> and the ſame Reward to this day remains for all the Negligent, Unfaithful and diſobedient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who will not improve their Gift and Talent committed unto them.</p>
            <p>Now, to ſpeak a little after the manner of men, and to compare Spiritual Things with Temporal; That as no Malady or Diſtemper of the Body can be healed without the Application of ſome ſuitable Medicine, and that only ſuch as can reach unto the grieved part; even ſo no viſible Preparatory or outward Exiſtence, can reach unto, or effectually heal a Wounded Soul, but the alone ſaving Health and Power of Jeſus; and whoſo makes a right Application of it, comes livingly &amp; experimentally to witneſs the bleſſed Effects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which are the ſame as in the dayes paſt, that is, to give Sight to the Blind, to cauſe the Deaf to hear, the Lame to walk, the Leper to be cleanſed, and the Tongue of the Dumb to be unlooſed, to praiſe the Name of the Lord, and to magnifie his great Power in the Land of the Living; and the Poor in Spirit have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96734:19"/>received the Everlaſting Goſpel of Peace, which is freely preached, and Life and Immortality is brought to Light thereby—Oh! the Day of Glad Tidings is come, and the Year of <hi>Jubile</hi> to the Priſoner of Hope, and to the Captives and Diſconſolate Souls is known, who had no Comforter in the Earth, nor any to be found that had the Tongue of the Learned, to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon in the needful time.</p>
            <p>But now has the Lord appear'd to comfort the <hi>Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in Sion, and to give Beauty for Aſhes, the Oyl of Joy for Mourning, and the Garment of Praiſes for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Heavineſs,</hi> Iſa. 61.3. Therefore lift up your Heads, ye mournful Travailers, <hi>who have been weeping as</hi> Rachel <hi>for her Children, and refuſed to be comforted becauſe they were not,</hi> Jer. 31.15. For the Comforter is now come, even the Spirit of Truth, which leads into all Truth all thoſe that are willing to follow him, who ſaith, <hi>I am come that you might have Life, and that you might have it more abundantly,</hi> John 10.10. and he will lead you by a Way you know not, where you ſhall not Err.</p>
            <p>Life from God, the Fountain of Life and Glory, is now come, and is entered into the Witneſſes; the Graves are opened, the Dead is raiſed, and they that hear his heavenly Voice, their Souls live unto him: This is the new Birth, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of on this wiſe, <hi>My little Children, of whom I travail in Birth again until Chriſt be formed in you,</hi> Galat 4.19. Here the Apoſtle travailed for the bringing forth of that holy Birth which is conceived by the holy Ghoſt, and is born of the Water and of the Spirit, and is made a new Creature in Chriſt; for (ſayes he) <hi>If any man
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96734:20"/>be in Chriſt, he is a New Creature:</hi> But <hi>Nichodemus</hi> (a Ruler of the <hi>Jews</hi>) who came unto Jeſus by Night, reaſoned carnally on this manner, <hi>How can a Man be born which is Old; can he enter again into his Mother's Womb and be born?</hi> How ignorant was this Teacher of <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning the Work of Regeneration? it was a ſealed Book and a Myſtery unto him, as it is to many Wiſe Profeſſors and Night walking <hi>Nichodemus</hi>'s of this Age, who though they pretend to high things, yet ſtumble at that which ſhould open their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and give them a true Diſcerning betwixt that which is born of the Fleſh, and that which is born of the Spirit; but are yet in the dark, and their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings vailed by reaſon of Sin and Tranſgreſſion, which ſtands as a Partition Wall unremoved, and the old man with his Deeds not put off, nor the new man (the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi>) put on, which bears the heavenly Image; and being gone aſtray and alienated from the Life of God in themſelves, they become not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with that which ſhould work a Change in their Hearts, not withſtanding all their Profeſſion of God and Chriſt in Words, whilſt in their Works they deny him. Now the birth of the fleſh is known by its fruits, which is Envy, Wrath, Murder and Perſecution of that Birth that is born after the Spirit, &amp; hath been ſo even from Righteous <hi>Abel</hi> to this very day: for <hi>Cain,</hi> who was the firſt that was born of a Woman, envyed his Brother <hi>Abel.</hi> and ſlew him (becauſe his Brother's Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was accepted, and his rejected) whoſe innocent Blood, from the Ground on which it was ſpilt, cryed in the Ears of the Lord for Vengence, as doth the Blood of the Innocent People of God this day cry unto
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96734:20"/>him, who will render Judgment and Vegeance upon the Enemies of his Righteous Seed and People, who have ſacrificed unto and worſhipped the Lord their God, according to his Commands, and the Requirings of his holy Spirit in their Hearts.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Iſhmael</hi> the Son of the Bond Woman (who was born after the Fleſh, and is in Bondage with her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) he was a Mocker, and Mocked <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who was the true Seed and Heir of the Promiſe; ſo all thoſe now, who are of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith, are of the true Seed, and inherit the Bleſſing and Kingdom prepared for them before the Foundation of the World.</p>
            <p>And again, you may read how <hi>Eſau</hi> (the firſt birth) who was a prophane man, and ſold his Birth-right for one Morſel of Meat, he ſet himſelf againſt <hi>Jacob</hi> (the ſecond Birth) who was of the true Seed and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Line, unto which the Promiſe and Bleſſings did deſcend and appertain.</p>
            <p>So here people may ſee, how that after man had tranſgreſſed and forſaken the Lord, he fell ſhort of the <hi>Bleſſings of God,</hi> and in that ſtate the firſt birth, which was of the Earth, earthly and ſenſual, was rejected with its Offerings and Sacrifice; ſo it is the ſecond birth, which is after the Spirit, that obtains the Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Haman,</hi> an Informer againſt <hi>Mordecai,</hi> was of this corrupt ſeed &amp; birth of the fleſh, whoſe Off-ſpring as well as himſelf has been perſecuting the Members of the true Church &amp; Seed of God for theſe many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years unto this very time, and all about Religion, Sacrifice and Worſhip: ſo that our Perſecutors, who have been rending and tearing (like Dogs and Bears) and perſecuting people for their Non-conformity and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96734:21"/>different Perſwaſions about Religion, may ſee their Off ſpring, and who was their Captain and General in this wicked Work, whoſe Spirit is alive though his Body be dead; and it will deceive them in the end: And Wo and Miſery will be the Portion of all ſuch (if not prevented by timely Repentance) at unawares, when 'twill be too late to call unto the Hills and to the Mountains to fall upon them and cover them from the Preſence of the Lord, and to hide them from his dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Majeſty and fierce Indignation, which is kindled againſt all the Enemies of his choſen People, who are unto him as the Apple of his Eye; and no Way will be found to eſcape his <hi>terrible Judgments:</hi> For <hi>ſuch as every one ſows, ſuch muſt they reap; and they that ſow to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap Corruption; but they that ſow to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reap Life Everlaſting,</hi> Gal. 6.8. And if they who are and perſiſt in <hi>Cain</hi>'s nature and <hi>Eſau</hi>'s ſpirit, ſeek a place of Repentance with Tears, as they did, they ſhall not find it, but ſhall be like <hi>Cain,</hi> who was a Fugative and a Vagabond in the Earth, being driven out from the Preſence of the Lord, and ſaid, <hi>My Puniſhment is greater than I can bear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! that people would but conſider what they are a doing, and to whom they yield their Members Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to obey, and follow that Exhortation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Rom. 6.13. <hi>Yield not your Members as Inſtruments of Unright couſneſs unto ſin, but yield your ſelves unto God; for the Wages of Sin is Death, but the Gift of God is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life.</hi> Now this Gift of God is freely extended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Mankind, in and by which he calls and excites to Purity and Holineſs, and to turn to him, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Sin, which makes the Separation, and to come out of Ungodlineſs and all Uncleanneſs.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:96734:21"/>
            <p> The Call of the Lord has reached unto all; but the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Have they not all heard? yes verily; their ſound went into all the Earth, and their words to the end of the World,</hi> Rom. 10.18. but all have not obeyed the Voice of the Lord. Oh! why will ye ſtand idle in the Market-place, pleading for and contending about out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Obſervations, Dayes and Times, and who ſhall have the greateſt Wages, as did thoſe whom Chriſt called into the Vineyard, who gives Liberally with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out upbraiding a Reward anſwerable to every ones Deſert; he is juſt and righteous in giving true Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and full Weight, and will reckon truly with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, and will bring all thy Deeds and Actions into thy Remembrance: If his Witneſs in thy Conſcience juſtifie thee, then may'ſt thou with Courage, Boldneſs and Joy appear before him; but if it condemn thee, then God is greater, who will in no wiſe hold thee guiltleſs in his ſight. And the ſluggiſh, idle and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Servants ſhall be clothed with the Rags of old <hi>Adam,</hi> and their Nakedneſs and Poverty will appear unto all: For when <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> had ſinned, they ſaw their Nakedneſs (and not before) for then they were naked and ſtrip'd of that Garment and Covering of Innocency, wherewith the Lord had clothed them at the firſt; and then they went to work, and made for themſelves Coverings of Fig-leaves, which was but a mean Covering, inſtead of the Garments of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and Holineſs, which the Lord had put upon them.</p>
            <p>And how inſident is it unto fallen Man and Woman to make Unrighteous Coverings for Sin, and (as <hi>Adam</hi> after Tranſgreſſion did) to hide themſelves under the Thickets and Shades of Excuſes and Pretences: But
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96734:22"/>the Lord will rip off all ſuch Coverings and Pretences; and We from him is pronounced againſt <hi>ſuch as are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and not with his Spirit, that they may add Sin unto Sin.</hi> Iſa. 30.1.</p>
            <p>But now is the Everlaſting Comforter come the Spirit of Truth, which leads the Believers and the Obedient into all Truth, of whom it is written on this wiſe, (as a ſignal Token, and to give full Aſſurance, that it is he who was promiſed) <hi>When he is come, he will reprove the World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs and of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: of Sin, becauſe they believe not in me; of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, becauſe I go to my Father, and ye ſee me no more; of Judgment, becauſe the Prince of this World is judged,</hi> John 16.8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>Therefore ariſe, ſtand up and make haſte, you who have been idle, and come into the Vineyard and Work of the Lord, who gives Light unto all, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may ſee what is the Work of the Day, and what is required of them; for, when the Night comes, no man can work for God: Therefore follow Chriſt, the Anointed of God, who is given for a Leader and a Commander unto the People, who is Jeſus, the Peaceable Saviour, who leads his People out of, and ſaves them from their Sins; he has been ſleighted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and ſet at nought by the Wiſe Maſter Builders; but unto a Remnant is he become the Head Stone of the Corner, Choſen of God, Elect and Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto all thoſe who have received him and believed on him. He is that Stone which <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> ſaw cut out of the Mountain without Hands, and is now growing great, and ſhall fill the whole Earth, and is ſtriking at the Feet of the great Image and Images,; and the power of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96734:22"/>Dragon, Beaſt &amp; Falſe Prophet is coming down apace, and <hi>Myſtery Bobylon,</hi> the Great Whore and Mother of Harlots, is now diſcovered, who has ridden upon the Beaſt (which by his power has defended her) and has made the Nations drunk with the Wine of her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, which ſhe had hold forth in her Golden Cup, who hath this Inſcription written in her Fore-head, <hi>Myſtery Babylon the Great, the Mother of Harlots and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 17.5. This Whore (the Falſe Church) has gone a Whoring from the Life and Power of God, and from Chriſt Jeſus the Ground the Apoſtles and primitive Church of God was built. And this falſe Church is that great Whore which <hi>John</hi> ſaw ſit upon the Waters (which are <hi>Nations, Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Tongues and People;</hi> who are not miſ-parallel'd to Waters, becauſe through the drinking of the Whore's Cup, they are become unſtable and wavering in their Minds and Judgments) and hence did ariſe Confuſion, like a troubled Sea, and great Combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which ended in Bloodſhed and Murder; and the Beaſt upon which <hi>John</hi> ſaw the Woman ſit, <hi>became Scarlet coloured;</hi> and he ſaw the Woman <hi>drunk with the Blood of the Saints, and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> that has been ſhed from Age to Age, and cryes in the Ears of the Lord for Vengeance, <hi>who will judge and avenge the Righteous Cauſe of the Faithful Followers of the Lamb, with whom the Dragon, Beaſt and Falſe Prophet have made War, becauſe they have kept the Commandments of God, and have the Teſtimony of Jeſus: But they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came by the Blood of the Lamb, and by the Word of their Teſtimony; and they loved not their Lives unto Death: Theſe are they who are not defiled with Women, but have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96734:23"/>come through great Tribulation, and have made white their Garments in the Blood of Jeſus:</hi> And we know the Lamb ſhall have the Victory: And <hi>he will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, &amp; overturn, until he come to reign whoſe Right it is; whoſe Kingdom is an Everlaſting Kingdom, and whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion endures throughout all Generations; and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this World ſhall become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall Reign forever and ever,</hi> Rev. 11.15.</p>
            <p>And Deſolation and ſudden Deſtruction is coming upon <hi>Babylon</hi> (the great City of Confuſion) <hi>and all her Inhabitants and Merchants, who have enriched them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by trading in her Wares and with her Coſtlineſs, ſhall weep and wail becauſe no man buyeth them any more; and they ſhall ſtand afar off for fear of her Torment, and eaſt Duſt on their Heads, and ſay, Alas, alas! the Great City, wherein were made Rich all that had Ships on the Sea by her Coſtlineſs; for in one Hour ſhe is made deſolate,</hi> Rev. 18.15, 19. And the Lord will dry up the Tongue of the <hi>Aegyptian Sea;</hi> and all the goodly Buildings and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Pictures, which men in their fallen Wiſdom and ſenſual Inventions have been erecting and ſetting up, muſt now be broken down and demoliſhed by thoſe Weapons which are not Carnal, but Spiritual, and mighty through God to the bringing down the ſtrong Holds of Satan, the Prince of Darkneſs. And thoſe whom the Lord has deliver'd out of this ſpiritual bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and from under the <hi>Aegyptian Task-maſters,</hi> and has open'd their Eyes to behold their miſerable Eſtate, and the great Deſolation that is coming upon them who are yet in this City, whoſe rotten Foundation is tottering and ready to fall; They cannot but call un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them and cry, <hi>Haſte, haſte, and eſcape for your Lives
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96734:23"/>out of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and flee to the City of Refuge,</hi> as juſt <hi>Lot</hi> did at the Warning and Call of the Angel of the Lord, <hi>to haſte out of</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>and flee to the little City</hi> Zoar; and how ſoon after was <hi>Sodom</hi> deſtroyed with Fire and Brimſtone! and how eminently was the Arm and Power of the Lord manifeſted in preſerving his People (to wit, <hi>Lot</hi> and his Family) in that day, who ſmote the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> which purſued his Meſſengers with Blindneſs, ſo that they could not find the Door to go into the Houſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.11. even ſo we have ſeen in our day, when the Lord hath ſent forth his Meſſengers and Servants from City to City, and from one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to another, to perſwade and exhort people, <hi>to ceaſe from the Evil of their Wayes, and to fear and obey the Lord that created them:</hi> How hath the Wicked, even <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> muſtered up their Forces againſt us, the <hi>Dragon</hi> and his Angels againſt <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels; but <hi>Michael</hi> our Prince ſhall have the Victory.</p>
            <p>And we have ſeen the Lord to ſmite the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> as he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, when they purſued the <hi>Iſraelies,</hi> and would not let them go free out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> according to the Mind and Will of the Lord, that they might Worſhip him; how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully did the Lord God appear for their Deliverance, to the dividing the Waters of the great Deep, that his choſen People might paſs through, and eſcape the Hands of their Enemies: <hi>The Sen obeyed his Command, and fled; and</hi> Jordan <hi>was driven back, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 14.22. Pſalm 114.3. and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt overturned in the midſt of the Sea, ſo that they ſaw the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> dead upon the Shore. Then they ſung the Song of high Praiſes to the Lord, and the Songs of Deliverance to the God of <hi>Iſrael,;</hi> whoſe mighty Wonders they had ſeen in the Deep. And many in this day can ſing a Melodious Song of High Praiſes to the God of their Salvation, upon the Banks of <hi>Sion,</hi> and upon the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the deep Senſe of his many great Preſervations and Miraculous Diliverances, which we have known ſince we were a People, by the ſaving Arm of his Power; unto which we aſcribe all the Honour and Glory of his own Works, who is God over all, worthy to be Magnified, and in the higheſt Praiſed forever and evermore.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:96734:24"/>
            <p> And as we have ſtood in his Counſel; when with Tribulations and Temptations on every hand we have been ſurrounded and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were whe nthe Sea was before them, and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> purſuing after them, and Hills and Mountains on every hand; yet ſtanding ſtill, and in Patience waiting upon the Lord, we have ſeen the great Salvation of God manifeſted in our greateſt Straits, and his Strength in our Weakneſs. And although we be but poor and deſpicable Inſtruments, as in the Eyes and Eſteem of the Wiſe and Prudent of this World, yet is the Wiſdom of this World Fooliſhneſs with God; and he is making choice of the Deſpiſed and Contemptible things of this World, to Confound the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, and to bring to Naught the Underſtanding of the Prudent; that no Fleſh may glory in his Preſence, before whom every tall Cedar and ſturdy Oak muſt how, and all Shrubs muſt be rooted up; not by Sword, nor by Spear, or any Carnal Weapon, but by the Word of God's Power, which is quick and powerful, ſharper than any two-edged Sword: which Word alſo is as a Fire and an Hammer to cut down, burn up and beat in pieces all the Ungodlineſs of Wicked men, that ſtands in Oppoſition to Him whoſe right it is to Reign in the Kingdoms of Men.</p>
            <p>And we have ſeen the Uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtims</hi> to fall Heaps upon Heaps, as they did by the hand of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who had no better Inſtrument of War than the Jaw-bone of an Aſs; which in outward appearance was very Contemptible; yet ſtanding in that living Faith which gives Victory, the Conqueſt is known. And this is that Word of Faith which the Apoſtles preached, by which the Juſt live to God, and is much more pretious than Gold that periſheth—One Grain of it (if no bigger than a Grain of Muſtard-Seed) is ſufficient to enable for an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter againſt the potent Enemy of the Soul: Although he come like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking his prey, in this Faith there is ſafety for the Righteous, by which the holy men of God ſtood and were upheld, when they fought the good Fight of Faith; and by which the Noble Warriors and Antients of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:96734:24"/>obtained a Good Report, and did many Valient Acts, and got Victory by and through it, by the ſtopping the Mouthes of Lyons, quenching the Violence of Fire, eſcaping the Edge of the Sword, out of Weakneſs were made Strong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And by this Faith, Women received their Dead raiſed to Life again, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 11.34, 35. And others were Tortured, not accepting Deliverance, that they might obtain a better Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>And it was by Virtue of this Living Faith, that <hi>David</hi> whilſt a Stripling, and a Keeper of his Father's Sheep, went forth againſt, and Encountred with <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> that Great Gyant, and Uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtim,</hi> who had defied the Armies of the Living God, and inſulted over them, becauſe of his Greatneſs and Strength; at which <hi>Saul</hi> was Diſcouraged. But ſays little <hi>David, Let no mans Heart fail becauſe of him; Thy Servant will go and fight with this</hi> Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtim. Now when <hi>Saul</hi> ſeemed to Diſcourage him, <hi>David</hi> anſwered and ſaid unto <hi>Saul, Thy Servant kept his Father's Sheep; and there came a Lyon, and likewiſe a Bear, and took a Sheep out of the Flock; and I went out and reſcued the Lamb, and ſlew the Lyon and the Bear. And this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed</hi> Philiſtim <hi>ſhall be as one of them, becauſe he railed on the Hoſt of the Living God.</hi> Moreover, he ſaid, <hi>The Lord that delivered me out of the Paw of the Lyon, and out of the Paw of the Bear; he will deliver me out of the Hand of this</hi> Philiſtin. So <hi>David</hi> went out againſt him (not with <hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour; For ſayes he, <hi>I cannot go with theſe, for I am not accuſtomed</hi>) with his Staff and his Sling, and Five SMOOTH Stones taken out of a Brook; and when the <hi>Philiſtim</hi> ſaw <hi>David</hi> come, he Diſdained him, being but a Boy, and for the Meanneſs of his Inſtrument of War, and ſaid, <hi>Am I a Dog, that thou comeſt to me with a Staff?</hi> with other Diſdainful and Approbious Language. But <hi>David</hi> anſwered, <hi>Thou comeſt to me with a Sword and with a Spear, and a Shield: But I come unto thee in the Name of the Lord of Hoſts, the God of the Armies of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>whom thou haſt defied; This Day will the Lord deliver
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96734:25"/>thee in to mine Hands, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Sam. Chapter 17. Read through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So David</hi> ſlew this great Gyant with a Sling and a ſmooth Stone out of his Pag, which was but a mean Inſtrument, yet being handled in the Faith, and Power of God, prevailed, and gave <hi>Iſrael</hi> Victory over their Enemies.</p>
            <p>Oh! how precious is this Faith, whereby the Righteous obtain Victory over both Inward and Outward Enemies from Generation to Generation?</p>
            <p>This is that Faith which cometh by Hearing, and Hearing by the Word of God; which Word is nigh thee, even in thy Heart and in thy Mouth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. And is the ſame Word unto which <hi>Moſes</hi> recommended and directed the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and earneſtly preſſed them to the keeping of the Commandment, and the Word in the Heart, and ſaid, <hi>It is</hi> NOT <hi>in Heaven, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, Who ſhall aſcend to bring it from thence?</hi> NEITHER <hi>is it beyond the Sea, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, Who ſhall go over to fetch it us? but the Word is very nigh thee, in thy Heart and in thy Mouth, for to do it. Behold, this day I have ſet before thee Life and Good, Death and Evil,</hi> Deuteronomy, Chap. 30. Verſe 12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>From whence I conclude, and am fully ſatisfied, that Life and Good conſiſts in, and is obtained by hearkening unto and obeying that Word that is nigh in the Heart. And on the contrary, by ſleighting and rejecting of it, Death and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil cometh upon the Souls of all thoſe who running after Empty Words and after the Tree of Knowledge, and come not to the Guidance of that Inward <hi>WORD</hi> in the Heart, which is able to give them Acceptance with the Lord.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Without Faith</hi> (viz. in this Word which purifies the Heart) <hi>it is impoſſible to pleaſe God;</hi> and by it we have Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs unto him. But a Dead, Hiſtorical or Notional Faith will profit none: But that which purifieth the Heart, and worketh by Love, and purgeth the Conſcience from Dead Works
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96734:25"/>(of which Chriſt is the Author and Finiſher too) that only will profit.</p>
            <p>And this True and Living Faith is known by the Bleſſed Effects and Works of it; for as the Body without the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is Dead, ſo Faith without Works is Dead alſo, <hi>James</hi> 2.26.</p>
            <p>And all thoſe that are true Believers in Chriſt Jeſus, the Lamb of God, that takes away the Sins of the World, they come to find the Powerful Operation of this Faith in his Blood to cleanſe and purifie them from all Filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, and hereby are made Veſſels of Honour, and fit Temples for the Lord to dwell in, being ſanctified through the Blood of Cleanſing, and Waſhed with pure Water, and made clean thereby; ſo that an Acceptable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and a Pure Offering is offered up unto God from a clean Veſſel, which is a Sweet Savour unto him, and well pleaſing in his Sight; and hereby we know that we are of God, becauſe we have Admittance into his Preſence, and free Acceſs to the Throne of his Grace; ſo that whatſoever we ask by Faith, and in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, it is granted unto us.</p>
            <p>And this Faith is the Gift of God, and is received and witneſſed in receiving Chriſt the true Light. But they that deny the Light, are Strangers to this Faith, and ſo are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Blood of Cleanſing, and of that which ſhould reconcile them to God, and diſcover unto them the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But my true deſire are, that all who in any meaſure are ſtirred up, and feel an inquiry and ſearch begun in their Hearts after the Lord and the knowledge of his Way, that ſuch may receive the word of Truth into their Hearts, and that it may be as Seed ſown upon good Ground, which takes Root downward and brings forth Fruit upward, and an Heavenly increaſe to God and Satisfaction and Comfort to their Souls may be witneſſed, that all old things may be done away, the old Heavens and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96734:26"/>the old Earth, with the beggarly Elements and Rudiments of the World, that the new Heavens and the new Earth may be known, wherein dwells Righteouſneſs, and Peace, and Joy in the holy Ghoſt. Oh! Priſe the Day of your Viſitation and let it not ſlip over your Heads unregarded, leſt it be ſaid unto you as it was to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of Old, <hi>How often would I have gathered you as a Hen gathers her Chickens under her Wings? But ye would not; Behold, your Habitation ſhall be left unto you deſolate,</hi> Matth. 23.37, 38. Now mark, 'twas not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they COULD not come unto Chriſt, (but becauſe they WOULD not) that they were left ungathered; there was a Senſual and Corrupt Will in them that would not be ſubject to him that called them, nor bow down their Necks to Chriſt's Yoke, but Stiff-necked and Rebellious were they, wherefore Chriſt withdrew himſelf, and ſaid unto them, <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ye ſhall not ſee me, untill ye ſay, Bleſſed is he that cometh in the Name of the Lord,</hi> verſ. 39.</p>
            <p>Now, conſider your Latter End, and labour to make your Calling and Election ſure, that when you come to render a final Account of the Deeds done in the Body to the Great and Mighty Judge of Heaven and Earth (before whoſe Tribunal Seat of Judgment All muſt appear) you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sentence of PEACE, and the Reward of WELL DONE GOOD AND FAITHFUL SERVANT, ENTER INTO THE JOY OF THY LORD. Oh! this will be a joyful Sentence, and more Eſtimable than all the Glory of <hi>Egypt</hi>-or the Treaſure of Ten Thouſand Worlds, where the Soul comes to poſſeſs an Everlaſting Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and a Crown of Life and Immortality a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96734:26"/>them that are ſanctified, where the Song of High Praiſes and Everlaſting Halelujahs is ſung to the God of their Salvation, who hath wiped away all Tears from their Eyes, and Sighing and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is fled away; Which are the true Breathings of her who deſires the Everlaſting Well-being of the Souls of all People,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iſabel Yeamans.</signed> 
               <dateline>Swarthmore, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 2d <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
